Think about a time when you felt very kind
and caring towards a person
or a beloved animal
Try not to choose a time
when that person or animal was very distressed
because then you are likely to focus on that distress
instead of the kind compassionate feelings for him or her
Next
focus on the desire to help the person or animal
and the feelings of kindness that will guide you to help
Remember that in this exercise
it is your intentions that are important
not how the person or animal responds
Bring to mind a specific time
when you felt compassionate towards him or her
imagine yourself expanding
as if you are becoming calmer
wise
stronger
more responsible
and able to help him or her
Pay attention to your body
as you remember how it felt to be kind
Spend some time expanding
with warmth in your body
Notice the genuine desire
for this person to be free of suffering
and to flourish
Spend a minute or two
thinking about the tone of your voice
and the kinds of things you said
or the kinds of things you did
or wanted to do to help
Spend another minute or two
thinking about how good it felt to be kind to him or her
Finally
focus only on your desire to be helpful
and kind
the sense of warmth
feelings of expansion
your kind tone of voice
the wisdom in your voice
and the wisdom in your behavior
When have finished this exercise
you might allow yourself to take these feelings of compassion
and kindness
into the rest of your day
and how you interact with others around you