try to create a sense of being a compassionate person
focus on your desires to become a compassionate person
and to be able to think
feel
and act compassionately
imagine yourself with each of the qualities of compassion
wisdom
strength
warmth
and responsibility
some days this will be easier than others
but hold on
to even the slightest glimmer of feeling like a compassionate person
next
think about someone you care about
it could be a partner or a friend
a parent or a child
or even a beloved animal
focus on them
and direct your attention towards them
with three basic feelings and thoughts
may you be well
may you be happy
may you be free from suffering
remember that it is your behavior and intentions
that are important
rather than how he or she will react
be gentle
take your time
and allow yourself to focus on the desires
and wishes
you create for this other person
it may help to picture them smiling
and sharing these feelings
spend some time
simply focusing on this genuine desire
for the other person to be happy