Memory can be a great tool
for provoking and practicing compassion
Begin with your compassionate posture
Find a comfortable position
You can close your eyes
or just look down
or have an unfocused gaze
Lift your shoulders up and back
and notice how this creates a concave curve in your back that lifts your diaphragm
When we ‘re stressed
the body tends to curl inwards
So here we open up the chest and body
Let the body support itself
rather than leaning or slouching Shoulders
Shoulders are in line with the hips
and feet are flat
on the floor or resting comfortably
a shoulders width a part
Everything is in line
We are sitting
or standing with dignity
confidence
and attention
Form a friendly expression on your face
as if you are showing friendship for someone you care about
Although this may feel unnatural to do
expressions can affect systems in your brain
and change the way you think or the way you feel
So now with our compassion posture
we are going to move gently
into soothing and grounding breathing rhythms
We breathe in gently through the nose
for around five seconds
noticing the stillness at the top of the breath
and then breathing out
for around five seconds
noticing the stillness at the bottom of the breath
We are breathing in
and out
through the nose
gently
not flaring the nostrils
easy in
and easy out
a nice smooth
and even
rhythm of breathing
Once you feel that your body has slowed down a bit
you might allow your body posture and facial expression
to become compassionate
Feel free to play around with postures and facial expressions
but whatever expression and posture you go with
they should be gentle
Once you are ready
think of a time when someone was kind to you
Not a time when you were in distress
just a time when someone was kind to you
A time when someone treated you with compassion
grace
dignity
or kindness
Put on your compassionate expression
and adopt the compassionate body posture
you have cultivated
as you remember the compassion you received
Recall how it felt to receive that kindness
Spend a minute thinking
about the expressions of the person who was kind to you
and mimicking them
if that helps
If you’re having trouble remembering them
imagine the person moving towards you
with a smile on their face
or their head tilted to one side
While recalling the memory
focus on the important sensory qualities
of your memory
Try the following steps
One
Focus on the kinds of things this person
said
as well as the tone of their voice when the spoke
Spend a minute thinking
about the kind things that this person said
Next
focus on the feeling of the emotion in the person
what they really felt for you at the moment
Focus on that for another minute
Finally
focus on the entire experience
Think about whether they touched you in a friendly or comforting way
or whether they helped you in some other way
Allow the experience of gratitude
and joy in being helped grow
inside of you
Remember to keep your expression as compassionate as you can
Spend a few minutes in this step
When you are ready
let the memory gently fade away
Come slowly out of the exercise
and allow this feeling of compassion
and kindness
to carry into the rest of your day
and your interactions with others
in your life