the compassionate self is a vital sense
of self to develop
both for your compassion for others
and for your compassion for yourself
once again
begin with your compassionate posture
find a comfortable position
you can close your eyes
or just look down
or have an unfocused gaze
lift your shoulders
up and back
and notice how this creates a concave curve in your back that lifts your diaphragm
when we are stressed
the body tends to curl inwards
so here we open up the chest and body
let the body support itself
rather than leaning against the back of the chair
shoulders are in line with the hips
and feet are flat on the floor a shoulders width apart
everything is in line
we are sitting with dignity
confidence
and attention
form a friendly expression on your face
as if you are showing kindness for someone you care about
so now with our compassion posture and expression
we are going to move gently
into soothing and grounding breathing rhythms
we breathe in gently
through the nose
for around five seconds
noticing the stillness at the top of the breath
and then breathing out
for around five seconds
noting the stillness
at the bottom of the breath
we are breathing in
and out
through the nose
gently
not flaring the nostrils
easy in
and easy out
when your body has slowed down a bit
and you feel ready to begin
imagine that you are a deeply compassionate person
think of all the qualities
you would ideally have
as that compassionate person
focus on your desires
to become a compassionate person
and to be able to
think
feel
and act compassionately
imagine yourself with each of the qualities of compassion
wisdom
strength
warmth
and responsibility
first
imagine yourself with a wealth of wisdom
this wisdom comes from your understanding
about the nature of life
of our bodies
and of our minds
spend some time thinking
about how much goes on inside of us
which is not our fault
next
when you have a grasp on how it feels to have this wisdom
imagine having a compassionate strength
allow you body posture to change
in order to match how this compassionate strength feels
imagine yourself as a person
that understands your own difficulties
and understands the difficulties of others
in a non-judgmental way
imagine yourself as a person
that has the confidence to be sensitive
and the tolerance to withstand difficulties
when you have added a sense  of strength to your wisdom
move on to focusing on warmth
imagine that you are a warm
and kind person
both to yourself
and to others
create a facial expression
to match your compassionate self
and try to keep it on as you work through the exercise
imagine yourself speaking kindly to someone
and note the tone of your voice
imagine reaching out to someone with warmth
and feel what that might be like
finally
imagine yourself with a sense of
responsibility
imagine that you have no interest in condemning
or blaming others
or yourself
imagine that you only want to do the best you can do
to help yourself
and help others through difficult situations
hold on to your compassionate facial expression
focus on the experience of committing yourself
to a compassionate path
remember that it doesn't matter
if you feel you actually have these qualities or not
just imagine that you have them
it may be difficult to imagine yourself with these qualities
but no one gains them overnight
like anything else
being wise
strong
warm
and responsible
comes with time and practice