start by finding your soothing
rhythm breathing
have a compassionate expression on your face
next
find a comfortable position
you can close your eyes
or just look down
or have an unfocused gaze
lift your shoulders up and back
and notice how this creates a concave curve in your back
that lifts your diaphragm
when we are stressed
the body tends to curl inwards
so here we open up the chest and body
let the body support itself
rather than leaning or slouching against the back of your chair
your shoulders are in line with your hips
and your feet are flat on the floor
shoulders width apart
everything is in line
we are sitting with dignity
confidence
and attention
form a friendly expression on your face
as if you are showing kindness
to someone you care about
so now with our compassion posture
we are going to move gently
into soothing and grounding breathing rhythms
we breathe in gently
through the nose
for around five seconds
noticing the stillness at the top of the breath
and then breathing out
for around five seconds
noting the stillness at the bottom of the breath
we are breathing in
and out
through the nose
gently
not flaring the nostrils
easy in
and easy out
recall a safe place
with all the sights
sounds
smells
and feelings that come with it
remind yourself that this is
your special place
and that it delights in your presence
create a compassionate
vision for yourself
it may be created out of the mist in front of you
or it may snap into existence
once you have the idea mind
it may be walking towards you with a smile
once you build a solid image of your
compassionate self
think about the qualities that your compassionate image holds
these questions
can help you build a good image
how would you like your ideal compassionate image to look?
would you want the image to look young?
old?
to be male?
or female?
perhaps your image is an animal
the sea
or light
how would you like your compassionate image to sound?
are there any other sensory qualities?
that would come with your compassionate image?
colors?
sounds?
how would you like your ideal compassionate image to relate to you?
what would help you sense their commitment and kindness to you?
lastly
how would you like to relate to your compassionate image?
remember that your compassionate image
wants you to be free from suffering
and to flourish
the compassionate self understands
that we are all doing the best we can
and  it understands that the emotions that pop up in our minds
are not our fault
experience what it is like to focus
on the feeling that another being values
and cares for you unconditionally
focus on the idea
that your compassionate self
is looking at you
with warmth and kindness
imagine that they have the following desires for you
that you be well
that you be happy
that you be free from suffering
practice this exercise
as much as you need
to tap into your compassionate self
and surround both yourself
and others
with love
acceptance
and compassion