This exercise
will guide you through the process
of creating a mental safe place.
Begin by finding a comfortable position.
You can close your eyes
or just look down
or have an unfocused gaze.
Form a friendly expression on your face
as if you are showing kindness
to someone you care about.
Lift your shoulders
up and back
and notice how this creates a concave curve in your back
that lifts your diaphragm.
When we are stressed
the body tends to curl
inwards.
So here we open up the chest and body.
Let the body support itself
rather than leaning
or slouching.
Shoulders are in line with the hips
and feet
are flat on the floor
a shoulders width apart.
Everything is in line -
we are sitting with
dignity,
confidence
and attention.
So now with our compassion posture
we are going to move gently
into soothing and grounding
breathing rhythms.
We breathe in gently
through the nose
for around five seconds
noticing the stillness at the top of the breath
and then breathing out
for around five seconds
noting the stillness
at the bottom of the breath.
We are Breathing in
and out
through the nose
gently,
not flaring the nostrils.
Easy in
and easy out.
Create a sense of calmness,
safety,
and peace
within yourself.
When your sense of calmness,
safety,
and peace is in place,
imagine looking around yourself.
What can you see?
Your safe and peaceful place
may be a beautiful forest
with leaves dancing on the breeze.
It may be by the ocean,
hearing the gently crashing waves
rolling in
and out
on a soft, sandy beach
It might be a special place for you,
like your grandmother’s kitchen when you were a child
or a special vacation place.
Wherever this place is,
focus on what you
can feel.
In your safe place,
you may feel sun on your face,
a breeze lifting your hair
or caressing your cheek
or the heat of a campfire burning.
You may feel sand between your toes
or the warmth of a cozy kitchen.
Next,
think about what you can hear.
You might hear rolling waves
or seagulls crying at the beach.
You might hear the fire crackling,
or the sounds of your grandmother baking.
Perhaps you hear the soft cries
of the birds in the trees
or the rustling of leaves
in the breeze.
Now focus on what you can smell.
Maybe you smell the fresh scent of pine,
the salty smell of the ocean,
the delicious scent of apple pie
baking in the oven,
or the smell of a crackling log fire.
Allow your body to relax
– your whole body,
which includes your face.
Let your face show your pleasure at being
in a safe place.
Finally,
imagine that your safe place
actually finds joy in your presence as well.
Feel how your safe place rejoices when you arrive
and feel your own pleasure at being there
mirrored back to it.
Create an emotional connection with this place
and return to it
whenever you need to feel safe
loved,
and at peace.