The human heart has extraordinary capacity to hold and transform the sorrows of life
into a great stream of compassion.
Compassion is the movement of concern and kindness in response to the difficulty of any living being.
Compassion arises when you allow the heart to be touched by the pain and need of another.
Allow yourself to sit still and in a centered and quiet way,
breathe softly and feel your body,
feel your heartbeat,
feel the life within you.
Feel how you treasure your own life, how you guard yourself in the face of your sorrows.
Now gently bring to mind someone close to you whom you dearly love,
picture them and feel your caring for them,
notice how you can hold them in your heart
then let yourself be aware of their sorrows, their measure of suffering.
Feel how your heart opens naturally moving toward them to wish them well,
to extend comfort, to share in their pain and meet it with compassion.
This is the natural response of the heart.
Along with this response begin to wish them well reciting the phrase:
may you be free from suffering, may you be at peace.
Wishing this to your loved one while holding them in your heart of compassion:
After you feel your deep caring for this person close to you
turn your compassion heart toward yourself
becoming aware of your own measure of sorrow,
your own measure of pain
and then recite the phrase:
may I be free from suffering, may I be at peace.
Again, may I be free from suffering may I be at peace.
Gently hold yourself in this heart of compassion:
may I be free from suffering, may I be at peace.
Then gently shifting extend your compassion to others you know,
picture your loved ones one at a time,
hold the image of each in your heart and be aware of their difficulties.
Begin to wish them well:
may you be free from suffering, may you be at peace.
Hold them in your heart of compassion
wishing them well:
may you be free from suffering, may you be at peace.
Now gradually open your compassion heart further
opening to your neighbors and all those who live far away
and finally to the brotherhood and sisterhood of all beings.
Let yourself feel how the beauty of every being brings your joy
and how the suffering of every being brings you pain.
Feel your tender-hearted connection with all of life and its creatures,
notice how it moves with their sorrows and holds them in compassion.
Let your heart become a transformer for the sorrows of the world,
fill your breath in the area of your heart
as if you could breathe gently in and out of your heart.
Feel the kindness of your heart and envision it with each breath.
Imagine that with your heart you can touch the pain of others,
that you could breathe out compassion.
With each breath wish all living beings well.
Extend your caring and merciful heart to them
wishing all:
may you be free from suffering, may you be at peace.
Again, wishing all living beings well:
Sit quietly here and let your breath and heart rest naturally as a
center of compassion in the midst of the world.
Now gently take a moment to return to the space that you're seated in
by opening your eyes and seeing all that is around you,
by hearing the sounds in the room,
by joining the world,
by being here and now in this space.
Thank you for doing this loving-kindness meditation.