You are invited to sit in a comfortable position with both feet on the floor, being alert but not rigid.
Begin by first noticing or paying attention to your body,
noticing that it is actively sensing the environment.
Notice that you can feel yourself sitting in the chair
and that you can feel your feet on the ground.
Also notice that you can feel the clothes on your skin and perhaps your jewelry.
Notice, too, that you might feel the bend of your knees or elbows.
Now, gently close your eyes or locate a place in front of you where you can gently rest your gaze, eyes half open.
Notice as you close your eyes that your ears tend to open.
Take a few moments and pay attention to all the sounds that you hear.
Notice each sound as it comes into your awareness.
Notice its quality and intensity.
Gently be aware of each sound as it comes and goes.
Now simply take a few moments to be aware of sound.
Now gently releasing your attention from sound, place your attention on sensations of the skin,
paying attention to any sensation at the skin that arises into your awareness.
This may be a sense of coolness or warmth,
this may be an experience of air on the skin.
It may be an itch or a tingling.
Simply be aware of all sensations that arise as you pay attention to sensation at the skin.
If you get distracted, gently return to being aware of sensing at the skin.
Now gently releasing your attention from sensations at the skin,
place your attention at the tip of your nose and begin to notice the sensation of air moving in and out of your nostrils,
paying attention to your breathing.
You may notice that the air coming in through your nostrils is slightly cooler than the air moving out of your nostrils.
Allow yourself to just gently follow your breathing,
paying attention to the gentle easy air as it passes in and out of your body.
As you attend to your breathing, you may also notice the rise and fall of your chest.
Simply be aware of the sensations of expansion and contraction, rising and falling.
Be your breathing.
If you become distracted by your thoughts, simply take a moment to notice where your thoughts took you.
Give a gentle “nod” to distraction and then without judgment, return your attention to your breathing.
If you get distracted a hundred times, bring yourself back one hundred times, returning to your breath.
Take the next few minutes to focus completely on breathing, attending to the rise and fall.
Now, gently releasing your attention from your breathing and bringing your attention back, return to hearing.
Take a moment or two to be aware of the sounds that you notice in the room.
Now releasing your attention from sound, gently focus on your body and how it feels to sit in the chair.
Notice the placement of your feet, arms and head,
picture what the room will look like and when you're ready,
rejoin the room by opening your eyes.
Thank you for doing this mindfulness exercise.