Please take a comfortable seat with your eyes closed or gently cast your eyes downward
and focus softly on a point a few feet in front of you.
Rest your hands on your thighs with your palms facing up or down.
Feel free to modify the position to fit the current needs of your body and mind.
Now gently become aware of your body
bringing non-judgmental awareness to sensations both within and outside of your body,
simply noticing that you are experiencing without focusing intensely on any particular experience.
You are now invited to bring your attention to your breath,
noticing your breathing at the belly or chest,
simply paying attention to the rise and fall
as you breathe in and out.
Keep returning to sensing your breathing in your chest or belly
with each rise and fall of your breath.
If you notice yourself becoming distracted,
simply return your focus to the rise and fall of your belly or chest,
noticing each breath as it passes in and out of your body.