First, remove distractions - let others know not to bother you.
Make yourself comfortable, so that your thoughts are on the image and nothing else.
Sit, or lie down, in a quiet, comfortable place.
Mentally scan your body for tense muscles.
If you find a muscle that tense, or clenched, relax it.
During the imagery exercise, involve all of your senses in the image: sight, sound, smell, touch, and taste.
Get completely focused.
The more focused you are, the better.
Close your eyes, or lower your gaze.
Imagine that you are walking down a path, into a lush forest.
As you walk along the path, you completely take in the sights, smells, and feel of the place.
All around you are trees, grasses, mossy ground cover and fragrant flowers.
You hear the soothing sounds of birds chirping, and the wind as it gently blows through the treetops.
You smell the rich dampness of the forest floor. The smells of moist vegetation and new growth.
Through gaps in the treetops, you see the sun high in the cloudless blue sky.
The sun is dispersed through the canopy of the treetops and filters down onto the forest floor, creating intricate patterns of light and shadow.
With each breath you take in this place, you feel a deep sense of peace and relaxation.
You soon come to a clearing.
There are several flat rocks in the clearing surrounded by a soft moss.
With each breath you take in this place, you feel a deep sense of peace and relaxation.
You soon come to a clearing.
There are several flat rocks in the clearing surrounded by a soft moss.
A small stream runs along the rocks.
You lie back on one of the rocks, or on the cushiony moss, and put your feet into the cool water.
You feel the warm sun and a gentle light breeze through your hair and across your skin.
The sparkling clear water rushes around multi-colored rocks, making little whirlpools and eddies.
You put your hand into the water and lift a handful to your lips.
The water is cool and refreshing.
You close your eyes and listen to the water trickling around the rocks. You bathe in the warm sun, and feel as though you're floating, relaxing deeper and deeper.
You allow yourself to let go of any concerns or worries, and to feel completely refreshed and rejuvenated in this place.
When you're ready, imagine that you slowly get up and leave the clearing.
As you walk back down the path through the forest, fully take in this place, and realize that you may return whenever you wish by the same path.
Each time you enter this place, you will feel relaxed and at peace.