First, remove distractions - let others know not to bother you.
Make yourself comfortable, so that your thoughts are on the image and nothing else.
Sit, or lie down, in a quiet, comfortable place, then, mentally scan your body for tense muscles.
If you find a muscle that's tense, or clenched, relax it.
During the imagery exercise, involve all of your senses in the image: sight, sound, smell, touch, and taste.
Get completely focused.
The more focused you are, the better.
Imagine yourself walking along an old country road - the sun is warm on your back, the birds are singing, the air is calm and fragrant.
After a few steps, you come across an old gate.
The gate creaks as you open it and go through.
Your bare feet feel the rough, weathered step.
You find yourself in an overgrown garden, flowers growing where they have seeded themselves, vines climbing over a fallen tree, green grass, and shade trees.
Breathe deeply, smelling the flowers.
Listen to the birds and insects.
Feel the gentle breeze, warm against your skin.
You walk leisurely up a gentle slope behind the garden, and come to a wooded area, where the trees become denser.
The air feels mild, and a bit cooler.
You become aware of the sound of a nearby brook.
You breathe deeply of the cool and fragrant air several times, and with each breath, you feel more relaxed.
Soon, you come upon the brook.
It's clear and clean as it tumbles over the rocks and some fallen logs.
You follow the path along the brook for a ways.
The path takes you out into a sunlit clearing where you discover a small but picturesque waterfall.
There's a rainbow in the mist.
You find a comfortable place to sit for a while; a perfect spot where you can feel completely relaxed.
You feel good, as you allow yourself to just enjoy the warmth and solitude of this peaceful place.
It's now time to return.
You walk back down the path, through the cool trees, out into the sun-drenched overgrown garden, one last smell of the flowers, and out the creaky gate.
You leave this secret retreat, for now, and return down the country road.
Then, back to the room, slowly open your eyes, and remember, you can visit this place whenever you wish.