find a comfortable position
you can close your eyes
or just look down
or have an unfocused gaze
lift your shoulders
up and back
and notice how this creates a concave curve in your back
that lifts your diaphragm
when we are stressed
the body tends to curl inwards
so here we open up the chest and body
let the body support itself
rather than leaning or slouching
your shoulders are in line with the hips
and feet are flat on the floor
or resting comfortably
a shoulders width apart
everything is in line
we are sitting with dignity
confidence
and attention
next
form a friendly expression on your
face
as if you're showing friendship
or affection for someone you care about
so now with our compassion posture
we are going to move gently into soothing and grounding breathing rhythms
we breathe in gently
through the nose
for around five seconds
noticing the stillness at the top of the breath
and then breathing out for around five seconds
noticing the stillness at the bottom of the breath
we are breathing in
and out
through the nose
gently
not flaring the nostrils
easy in
and easy out
bring yourself to a sense of calm
and allow yourself to simply breathe
and simply be
when you're ready to move on
imagine a color that you associate with compassion
kindness
or warmth
there are no rules on what this color can be
it will likely be different for everyone
it only needs to remind you of compassion
imagine this compassionate color surrounding you
once it has surrounded you
imagine it entering through your
chest
near your heart
and slowly spreading through every inch of your
body
if this imagery doesn't call to you
try imagining a mist
or beam of light made of this color
that slowly drifts or flows through you
as the color permeates your body
focus on this color is one of wisdom
strength
warmth
and total kindness
create an expression on your face
that matches the feelings of this color
and allow yourself to keep this expression on your face
as you practice this exercise
as you imagine the color flowing through you
focus on the feeling that this color sole purpose
is to help you
strengthen you
and support you
allow yourself to feel supported
and loved