this exercise
can be focused on two different parts of yourself
a part of you that sometimes feels troubled
and a part of you that sometimes feels anxious
it will help if you've already tried
some of the other compassion exercises in this app
so that you can imagine
yourself
as a completely compassionate person
full of wisdom
strength
warmth
and responsibility
start by coming to a quiet and
contemplative place
notice how your body feels
and focus on your facial expressions
form a friendly expression on your face
as if you are showing friendship for someone you care about
for the first part of this exercise
we'll focus on the part of you
that sometimes feels troubled
imagine that you are watching a video of yourself
like you're watching a movie
you watch yourself get up in the morning
moving around your bedroom
and preparing yourself for the day
notice when or how the person you are
watching
might be troubled by self critical
thoughts
be in touch with their struggle
but don't get dragged down into it
keep your compassionate self forward
looking through the eyes of compassion
and with the intention of being warm
kind
and helpful
as you watch
try to be aware of how you
the person in this home movie
feels critical
troubled
or feels difficult emotions
as they go about their day
as the viewer
you can see the things that trouble this person
and you can allow yourself to have compassion for them
if you sense your compassionate self wandering away
let the imagery fade
and go back to the first exercise
recapture your compassionate
expression
in your upright posture
to begin again
this exercise
can help you adopt a more objective view of yourself
and your struggles
a very difficult thing to do
can also help you develop your own intuitive wisdom
and abilities to heal
to become more accepting of yourself
for the second version
the focus will be on your anxious self
whether you have a diagnosis
of anxiety or not
you likely struggle with some anxiety
this exercise can help you tap into your compassion
for your anxious self
like you did with your troubled self
spend a few minutes engaging your compassionate self
feel yourself slowing down
and adopt your compassionate expression
next
imagine yourself in a situation where you become anxious
remember to keep your compassionate position
look at your anxious self through the eyes of your compassion self
in practice compassion for the person that you see
understand and empathize with your anxious self
and extend compassion to him or her
imagine how you might like to help that person
what you might want to say to help them deal with their anxiety
you might say something to validate their emotions
or you may say something encouraging
to help them recognize their ability
to pull through the anxiety
whatever you say
make sure that it's kind
and helpful
imagine time gradually moving
and see yourself gradually reducing your anxiety
until enough time has passed
that the anxiety is all gone
get a sense of how it feels to have come through an anxiety episode
and offer your anxious self
some encouragement and understanding
later
when you're in a situation that is causing your anxiety to spike
spend a few moments
slowing down
reminding yourself of your compassionate self
and seeing yourself through the eyes
of compassion