Find a comfortable position
You can close your eyes
or just look down
or have an unfocused gaze
Lift your shoulders up and back
and notice how this creates a concave curve in your back
that lifts your diaphragm
When we are stressed
the body tends to curl inwards
So here
we open up the chest and body
Let the body support itself
rather than leaning or slouching
Shoulders are in line with the hips
and feet are flat on the floor
or resting comfortably
a shoulders width apart
Everything is in line
we are sitting with dignity
confidence
and attention
Form a friendly expression on your face
as if you are showing friendship for someone you like
Although this may feel unnatural to do it like this
your expressions can affect systems in your brain
and change how you think or feel
So now with our compassion posture
we are going to move gently
into soothing and grounding breathing rhythms
We breathe in gently through the nose
for around five seconds
noticing the stillness at the top of the breath
and then breathing out for around five seconds
noting the stillness at the bottom of the breath
We are Breathing in
and out
through the nose
gently
without flaring of the nostrils
Easy in
and easy out
a nice
smooth
even rhythm of breathing
Remember that it is okay for your mind to
wander
just notice where it wanders
and gently guide it back to awareness of your body
Feel the air flowing in and out of your nostrils
and simply allow yourself to be
If you find yourself stuck on noticing your breathing
let yourself focus on an object instead
You can hold something like a smooth stone
or a soft ball
something that feels good to hold
Focus on the object as well as your breathing
and note the way it feels to hold the object
Take the next minute
to allow yourself to find your nice
slow
even rhythm of breathing
When you’re ready
slowly open your eyes
and bring yourself back to the present moment
A small stretch
and a deep breath
can help you ready yourself for the rest of your day