Start this exercise by finding a comfortable position sitting in a chair, or lying on a bed or the floor.
Close your eyes and take a few deep breaths.
Relax.
Don't let yourself drift off to sleep during this exercise, but allow yourself to rest.
Now slowly bring your awareness to the tips of your fingers.
Feel your fingers.
Now, rub your fingertips together.
How do they feel?
Can you feel the small indentations on that are your fingerprints?
Take your time and try to feel them.
What do they feel like?
Are your fingertips raw from lots of work or are they smooth?
How does it feel to rub them together?
Notice the sensations.
Now rest your fingers where they were before.
What are they touching?
Are they resting on a blanket, on the arms of your chair, on your legs or stomach, or something else?
What does that feel like?
Is it soft or hard?
Does it have any other distinguishing features or textures?
Take the time to completely absorb the way these objects feel to your fingertips.
Now bring attention to your hands and arms. What do they feel like?
Perhaps they are relaxed and heavy.
Perhaps they are tense from work or stress.
Either way is okay.
There is no need to judge; simply observe the feelings in your arms and hands.
Are there any aches or pains?
Take note of these, but don't fixate on them. Simply notice the pain and move on.
Move your attention down to your toes now.
Wiggle them around a little. Are they in shoes or socks?
Are they free to move about?
Wiggle them and notice whatever is around or under them.
Do you notice air, or the feeling of blankets or socks?
Be aware of the experience.
Just notice the sensations as you bring your awareness to your feet.
Now shift your attention, and notice how your head is positioned.
Is it upright or tilted?
Is your head turned in a particular direction?
Simply notice your head's positioning without trying to change it.
Also notice any sensations that you are experiencing in your head or neck, such as tension or relaxation.
Take your time noticing.
What about your face? How does your face feel?
There are all kinds of sensations to explore here.
Think about your brow. Is it smooth and flat or is it wrinkled up with stress?
Again, don't try to change it, just notice it.
Now bring awareness to your nose. Can you breathe freely?
Think about your brow. Is it smooth and flat or is it wrinkled up with stress?
Again, don't try to change it, just notice it.
Now bring awareness to your nose. Can you breathe freely?
Take a few breaths in and out through your nose.
Can you feel air flowing into your nose?
Is the air warm or cool?
Pay attention to these feelings for a moment.
Then think about your mouth.
How is it positioned?
Is it pursed? Open? Closed?
What about the inside of your mouth? Is it wet or dry?
Explore all of the sensations throughout your face.
Perhaps your skin feels dry, or you notice other sensations of itching, tingling, heaviness, heat, or coolness.
Perhaps there are no feeling at all. Just notice.
Now bring your attention to your chest and belly.
Place one hand on your chest and one hand on your belly.
Can you feel your body breathing? What is that like?
Are you breathing fast or slow?
Is your breath going more into your belly or your chest?
Now breathe in through your nose and out through your mouth.
How does that feel?
Now invert that pattern, breathing in through your mouth and out through your nose, and notice how that feels.
Now breathe naturally, just noticing the sensations.
Next place your hands wherever they were before and expand your attention to include your whole body.
Where are you sitting or lying?
Can you feel the back side of your body touching the chair or bed in various places?
Be mindful of the way your body is positioned.
There is no need to move, just observe.
Now, with your eyes still closed, imagine the room you're in.
Where are you positioned in the room?
Do you have a sense of where the door is?
Can you feel your body in the larger space?
When you are ready, open your eyes and look around the room.
You can move if you wish.
Notice where the various pieces of furniture and decoration are.
What do they look like?
You can spend as much time as you like investigating different aspects of the room.
Remember not to judge, just to notice.
Whenever you are ready, you can stop this exercise and continue with your day.