To start this body scan, sit in an alert position or lie down.
When your mind wanders, gently bring it back to the words being spoken,
returning to whatever is you’re being asked to be aware of.
Practice non-judgment, practice acceptance.
Begin by closing your eyes, or by finding a place on the floor in front of you to gently rest your gaze.
Now gently turn your attention to your toes.
Wiggle them for just a moment to help you get your focus there.
Now slowly begin to scan from your toes to the bottom of your feet,
feeling the balls and the arches and the heels.
Now circle your attention around to the top of your feet,
taking a moment to notice that you can sense that area of your body.
You can be aware of the top of your feet.
Begin to scan further up to the ankles,
taking a moment to notice the sensation that is present at the ankles.
It may be one ankle first and then the other,
just gently be aware of any sensations you notice here.
Now, gently scan up to your calves,
becoming aware of your calves and noticing any sensations that you experience here.
It may be one calf first and then the other,
just gently be aware
noticing sensation at the calves.
Then wrap your attention around to the front of your lower legs, taking a moment to notice your shins,
be aware of any sensations that you experience here.
Scanning further up, place your attention on your knees,
notice any experience at your knees
and then gently scanning upward, move to your thighs,
feeling the sensation at your thighs.
Notice that you can experience sensation wherever you place your attention,
even if the sensation is soft and barely detectable.
And now, shifting your attention again, gently circle around to the backs of your legs,
feeling the area of your quadriceps,
noticing any sensation at the back of your legs.
Now gently scan up to your hips,
feeling the bend of your hips or the position of the hips if you are lying down.
Notice any sensations, any experiences that arise here.
Now gently scan around to your lower back,
feeling any sensation in that area of your body,
being aware of your lower back.
Now gently scan around to the front of your body, becoming aware of your abdomen,
noticing any sensations that you experience here.
Now scanning upward, notice your stomach,
gently placing your attention on the area of your stomach,
noticing all that rises and falls, all that you experience.
Now gently scanning higher, become aware of your chest.
Notice how it rises and falls as you breathe,
gently allow yourself to be aware of each sensation of the chest.
Now gently circle around to the middle of your back,
paying attention to whatever you experience as you notice the middle of your back.
Now gently scanning upward, notice the area of your upper back and shoulder blades.
Gently rest your attention on this part of your body.
Scan out across your shoulders, noticing any sensation that arises here,
any experience that you become aware of.
Gently move your attention to your upper arms, noticing the area of the biceps.
Be aware that you can feel sensation here,
simply noticing.
Now wrapping around to the back of your arms, notice the area of the triceps.
Notice that you can experience sensation on the upper part and backside of your arms.
Scanning further, move your attention to your elbows,
noticing any sensation that you experience here,
noticing the bend if your elbows are bent,
or notice what it feels like if your arms are straight.
Simply be aware of sensation at your elbows.
Now gently scan down to your lower arm, noticing the tops of your lower arms.
And then gently circle around to the bottom,
noticing the area at the bottom of your lower arms.
Now scanning further, gently move to your wrists,
simply being aware of any sensation that you experience here.
It may be one wrist and then the other,
simply be aware of the sensation at your wrists.
Scan further out to the palms of your hands,
becoming aware of any sensation that you experience at the palms.
Notice your palms as your hands gently rest.
And then gently scan to the fingers,
noticing any sensation at the knuckles
or any other experiences that arise as you turn your attention here.
Scan right out to the tips of your fingers,
noticing any sensation at the tips of your fingers.
Now gently releasing your attention from the tips of your fingers,
place your attention on the base of your neck.
Begin to scan upward, noticing your neck,
and then the base and back of your head.
Now gently scan around to the front of your head,
becoming aware of your chin.
Gently place your attention at the chin,
being aware of any sensation you experience here.
Begin to slowly scan upward, noticing your lips,
your nose,
your cheeks,
your eyes,
your forehead,
and then continue scanning upward right to the top of your scalp,
becoming aware of the sensation that you experience right at the top of your head.
Now gently releasing your attention from the sensation at the top of your head,
take a moment and notice your whole body sitting in the chair or lying down.
Be aware of the sensations of pressure,
noticing where your body touches the chair
and noticing where it does not touch.
Now releasing your attention from your body,
gently place your attention on the image of the room that you are in,
and when you are ready, open your eyes.
Thank you for doing this body scan awareness exercise.