Start this exercise by sitting comfortably in a chair with your feet squarely on the floor.
Sit with your posture firm, but not rigid.
Make sure your head feels centered over your shoulders and place your arms in a comfortable position at your sides or on your lap.
This posture helps you stay alert and focused.
Begin by noticing that your body is sensing the environment around you.
Notice that you can feel yourself sitting in your chair.
Feel your feet on the ground
and feel your clothes on your skin.
You might feel the bend of your knees or elbows.
Now, gently close your eyes, or locate a place in front of you where you can let your eyes rest, like the floor or a wall.
Notice that as you close, or soften, your eyes, your ears tend to open and sound is more available to you.
Take a few moments to pay attention to all of the sounds that you hear.
Now gently release your attention from the sounds around you.
Place your attention on the tip of your nose, and then begin to pay attention to the sensation of air moving in and out of your nostrils.
Notice the change in temperature between the in breath and the out breath.
Allow yourself to gently follow your breathing, paying attention to the air passing in and out of your body.
You may also notice the rise and fall of your chest and belly as you breathe.
Feel that expansion and contraction.
Relax into your breathing, and allow it to be natural and unforced.
If you become distracted by your thoughts, just take a moment to notice where the thoughts took you.
Then, without judgment, let go and return your attention to your breathing.
If you get distracted 100 times, that's ok - just bring yourself back to your breath 100 times.
Now, take the next few minutes to attend completely to your breathing.
You won't hear my voice for the next 5 minutes.
Now gently release your attention from your breathing and bring your focus back to hearing.
Take a moment to be aware of the sounds around you.
Now, releasing your attention from sound, gently focus on the sensations in your body.
Notice the placement of your feet, arms, and head.
When you are ready, open and refocus your eyes. Gently begin to move and go on with your day.