Start this exercise by sitting comfortably in a chair with your feet squarely on the floor.
Sit with your posture firm, but not rigid.
Make sure your head feels centered over your shoulders and place your arms in a comfortable position at your sides or on your lap.
This posture helps you stay alert and focused.
Now, gently close your eyes, or locate a place in front of you where you can let your eyes rest, like the floor or a wall.
Gently bring your attention to the natural rhythm of your breathing.
Simply notice your breath as you inhale and exhale.
You may notice the breath coming in and out through your nostrils, or you may focus on the sensations in your chest and belly rising and falling as you breathe.
There is no need to make the breath faster or slower, deeper or shallower.
Just allow breathing to happen.
Simply allow the natural pace of your breathing as you continue to pay attention.
Now imagine that you are sitting next to a small stream on warm autumn day.
As you gaze at the stream, you notice a number of large leaves of varying colors and shapes drifting along,
each at its own pace, one by one, in the slowly moving current.
Allow yourself to simply be with this scene for a moment, observing.
Now, gradually bring your awareness to what's going on inside you - thoughts, sensations, feelings, desires, impulses.
Now, bring your attention particularly to what's happening in your mind.
As you do, gently notice the thoughts that show up.
You may notice judgments, plans, and memories,
fantasies, resentments, worries, and other thoughts.
Notice all your thoughts with an attitude of compassionate allowing.
Bring the stream back to your awareness.
As thoughts come into your mind, notice them, and gently place them one by one on each large leaf passing by in the stream.
Observe each leaf as it comes closer to you.
Then watch as it moves away, drifting along and carrying that thought out of sight downstream.
Return to gazing at the stream, waiting for the next leaf to float by.
Continue placing each thought on its own large leaf.
Observe each one as you let it float away downstream.
When you are ready to end this exercise, shift your attention to the sounds around you.
Then shift your attention to your breath, and the rise and fall of your chest and belly as you inhale and exhale.
Now picture what the room you are in looks like, and when you are ready, open, or refocus, your eyes and look around.
Take your time before you go on with your day.